Guide to the Loren R. Mosher Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Loren R. Mosher papers
1933-2004
SC0818
Mosher, Loren R., 1933-
10 Linear feet
Biographical material, correspondence, articles and papers, reports, interviews, photographs, and audiovisual material relating to Loren R. Mosher, a clinician specializing in the treatment of schizophrenia without drugs.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
Collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 24 hours in advance of intended use.
Biography / Administrative History
Loren R. Mosher, clinician specializing in the treatment of schizophrenia without drugs, earned his undergraduate degree in biological sciences at Stanford University in 1956. His professional posts have included first chief of the National Institute of Mental Health's Center for the Studies of Schizophrenia (1968 to 1980); chief medical director of mental health service in Montgomery County, Md., (1988 to 1996); and clinical director of mental health services for San Diego County (1996 to 1998). He also served as clinical professor of psychiatry at UC-San Diego School of Medicine. He died in 2004.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection is arranged in two series: Series 1 Papers and Series 2 Publications. Biographical materials in Series 1, 1933-2004, include a diary from his 1973 trip to USSR, several interview transcripts, and his 1998 resignation from the APA with related correspondence. Correspondence in Series 1, 1965-2004, is arranged by name and subject; correspondents include Manfred Bleuler, Jerker Hanson, Theodore Itten, Noel Cobb, R. D. Laing (1 letter, 1965), Lars Martensson, Daniel R. Moynihan, and Karl Menninger (1 letter, 1973). Articles and papers in Series 1 are in typescript form dating from 1961 to 1999 and include a book manuscript on Soteria. Subject files in Series 1 contain articles, correspondence, reports, and memos; of note are Mosher?s interviews with Medard Boss and Manfred Bleuler, 1988; papers on existential psychiatry by Medard Boss, George Serban, and Paul Tillich (typescript); and reports, manuals and notes on Soteria, 1972-92. Other materials in Series 1 include photographs of Mosher, 1973-2000 and undated; slides of illustrations for talks; audio and video cassette tapes of talks, 1976-98; and DVDs on Mosher?s career. Series 2 contains published versions of his work (journal articles and books), with some related correspondence.
Access Terms
Bleuler, Manfred; Boss, Medard, 1903-; Laing, R. D. (Ronald David), 1927-1989; Martensson, Lars.; Menninger, Karl A. (Karl Augustus), 1893-1990; Tillich, Paul, 1886-1965; Community mental health services.; Schizophrenia.
Collection Contents
- Papers, Series 1; 12 box(es)
  - Biographical
    - Biographical outline/notes (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Biographical write-ups, 1998-2001 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Obituaries/Memorial programs (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Reports on visits to USSR (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Notes: Russian trip October, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Moscow diary, USSR trip, Oct. 5-29, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Trip report: Moscow, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Travel documents for trip to Russia, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Mosher interview by Craig Fees, Nov. 1993 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Petra Hohn, "'Being with' Loren Mosher," in Swedish and English, circa 1994 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Outsideren - translation of 1998 interview by Swend Balle with cover letter (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Clippings, 1970-79 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Clippings, 1982-88 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Clippings, 1991-99 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Clippings, 2000-2004 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Clippings, and fragment, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Mosher, Loren R.: presentations by (announcements, flyers, brochures etc.) (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Acta Psychiatrica Scandinavica. Supplementum. No. 413, Vol 106 - Program from 3rd International Conference on Early Psychosis [LM presented talk], 2002 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Diplomas and awards, 1933-52 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Certificates and awards, 1960-70s (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Certificates and awards, 1980s (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Certificates and awards, 1990s and undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Notebook: Messages to Loren from All Your Friends at the Department of Addiction, Victims and Mental Health Services, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Speeches, correspondence, articles re Mosher's time in San Diego, 1996-98 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - APA - Mosher's letter of resignation, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - APA resignation, related correspondence (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - APA resignation: articles by others (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Mosher's APA resignation letter as reprinted in other publications (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence (by name and subject)
    - Bleuler, Manfred - correspondence, 1975-93 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Hanson, Jerker - correspondence, 1995 1999 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Theodor Itten & Noel Cobb - correspondence re their Laing book project, 1989-2001 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Laing, R.D. - correspondence (1 letter received, 1 letter outgoing), 1965 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Martensson, Lars - correspondence (with some clippings and presentation re parcel of land in California) (1 of 2), 1990-97 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Martensson, Lars - correspondence (with a few articles) (2 of 2), 1990-97 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Mosher/Schreiber Christmas letter, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence with White House (a letter from Daniel R. Moynihan), 1969 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence A-B, 1973-2000 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence C-E, 1986-2001 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence F-H, 1973-2003 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence J-M (including 1 from Karl Menninger), 1971-2001 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence N-R, 1986-2001 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence S-Y, 1973-2001 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence: email, 1998-2001 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence: email, 2001-2004 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, miscellaneous (1 unsigned incoming letter, and 2 outgoing) (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - APA/Psychiatric News - correspondence, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - APA/Psychology Today - correspondence, 1987-99 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Psychology Today article ("Are Psychologists Betraying their Patients?") and Mosher's correspondence, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence (email) re "Are Psychologists Betraying their Patients?", 1999 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence re and with Family Therapy Forum, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence re Mosher's nomination for Foundation's Peace Prize, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Laing essay, related correspondence (includes a few from Theodor Itten), 1986-99 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - AMI (Alliance for the Mentally Ill)/NAMI - correspondence (pro and con) re Mosher's appointment as Associate Director of Addiction, Victim, and Mental Health Services (District of Columbia), 1988 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - NAMI (National Alliance for the Mentally Ill) - correspondence of Elaine Brooks, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - NAMI related correspondence, 1987-2001 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - European Soteria projects, correspondence and miscellany, 1995-2000 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Possible Soteria's, email correspondence, 2001-2004 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence about Mosher, 1994 1997 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence: copy of letter from Gregory Bateson to Mitchell Ginsberg re Ginsberg's essay "On Behavior and Communication,", 1969 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Letter to editor of Washington Post (clipping) "Notes on the Riddle of Schizophrenia,", 1970 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Letters to newspapers, 1970-71, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Letters to Psychiatric News (original and printed forms), 1975-90 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Letters to editor (New England Journal of Medicine) re Mosher's "Alternatives to Psychiatric Hospitalization," [clipping], 1984 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Letter to Behavioral Healthcare Tomorrow [printed], June 1999 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Letter to Los Angeles Times in response to Dr. Ely's article "How Patients Rights Can Harm Treatment,", 2002 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Notes
    - Notes, drafts, comments by others, 1970s-80s (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Notes, drafts, 1980s (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Notes on Buddhism, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Notes [residential alternatives], 1989 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Notes, circa 2000 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Miscellaneous essays, 1993 and undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - "What Everyone Taking a SSRI Needs to Know" - notes and draft, undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - "Big Pharma: Facts and Figures" [outline], 2003 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Articles, papers, etc. by Mosher (typescripts, arranged by date)
    - "The Career Schizophrenic: Psychiatry's Creation?", undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - "Deinstitutionalization American Style,", undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - "The Incomprehensibility of Madness,", undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - "Kingsley Hall as Experienced by a Member of the American Establishment,", undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - "Living with Our Madness,", undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - "The Myth of the Magic Pill," [chapter 6 of larger work], undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - On schizophrenia, draft, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - "Schizophrenia - Psychiatry's Sacred Symbol and Theoretical Graveyard," co-authored with Volkmar Aderhold, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - "The Several Worlds of Schizophrenia: Is a Synthesis Possible,", undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Soteria book, typescript chapters (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - "Unhappy Families," co-authored with John Read and Fred Seymour [chapter 17 of larger work], undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Title pending ["In the past decade or so a fascinating new economic, political and ideologic alliance has evolved within the mental health field."], undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Existential psychiatry - several papers and outlines by Mosher, 1961-62 and undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - "Report of the Departing Ward Chief, Fourth Floor: An Antihospital Ward in a Community Mental Health Center,", 1968 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - "Psychiatry - on the way out?" drafts, 1970 and undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Schizophrenia - drafts of several chapters, 1971 and undated (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - "Schizophrenia and Crisis Theory,", 1972 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - "A New Treatment for Schizophrenia: Does It Work?" draft, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Introduction to Approaches [book by unnamed author], with related outgoing letters, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - "Implications of Family Studies for the Treatment of Schizophrenia," symposium paper with related correspondence, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - "Neuroleptics, Dopamine Hypersensitivity and Exacerbation of Psychosis,", 1977 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - "Soteria's Model of Madness: Implications for Treatment,", 1977 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - "Social Barriers to Innovation,", 1977 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - "A Residential Non-hospital Interpersonal Treatment for Schizophrenia,", 1977 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - "What Is Schizophrenia?", 1982 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - "Schizophrenia and the Family,", 1988 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - St. Bart's 1989 [report on difficulties at DAVMHS] (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - "Schizophrenia: Current Myths; the Case of the Neuroleptic Drugs,", 1989 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - "An Anti-Psychiatrist's Contribution to Contemporary Psychiatry: A Personal Memoir," [re R. D. Laing] 1990 with related letter from Delty (?) (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - "The Mythological Effects of Neuroleptic Drugs,", 1995 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - "The Influence of Research on Health Policy: Walking the Razor's Edge; Some Things are Better Left Unsaid," Second Annual Dr. Ephraim T. Lisansky Lecture, University of Maryland School of Social Work, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - "R. D. Laing and Alternative to Mental Hospitals," draft and comments, 1997-98 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Lucca/Preface/LRM, Feb. 1999 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Mosher: Psychiatry, Drugs and the APA - draft and contract with Psychology Today, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - "The Biopsychiatric Model of 'Mental Illness': A Critical Bibliography," and several pages of other bibliographies, 2001 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - "Soteria-California and Its American Successors: Therapeutic Ingredients," with related correspondence, 2003-04 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous Mosher writings (photocopies, marked deposition exhibit 19, 23, 24) (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Subject Files
    - Apter, Nathaniel S. "Discussion of Loren Mosher's 'Implications of Research in the Psychosocial Treatment of Schizophrenia,'", 1981 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Mosher interviews of Medard Boss and Manfred Bleuler, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence with Medard Boss (n.d.) and the Boss family, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence with Gregor Becker-Bogemann re Boss interview, 1994-95 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence re publishing Boss/Bleuler interviews, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Breggin, Peter - article in MindFreedom, Winter 2002-03 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Community Mental Health - reviews and correspondence, 1989-91 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Community Mental Health - reviews and correspondence, 1989-95, 2001 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Community Mental Health Seminar outlines, 1995-96 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Conference in Mosher's honor (Mental Health Practice in the Nineties: Changes and Challenges), 1993 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Criteria for judging public mental health programs - prepared for Virginia Consumers Annual Meeting, June [no year] (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - DSM, various writings relating to (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Esalen Conference Report (Community Based Alternatives to Institutional Psychiatric Care), 1987 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Existential psychiatry - work by Medard Boss (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Existential psychiatry - work by George Serban (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Existential psychiatry - work by Paul Tillich (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - R. D. Laing memorials and obituaries (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Memo [from chief, Center for Studies of Schizophrenia] re NIH report, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Miscellaneous articles (not by Mosher) (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous items (2 poems, note re a quote for Mosher, and a sketch) (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - NAMI materials, 1990-2001 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Psicoterapias e Intervenciones Precoces en la Esquizofrenia; Homenaje a Loren R. Mosher 2004 [bibliographic dossier of Mosher's work for attendees at annual course on schizophrenia held in Madrid] (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Poster: Seminario La Riabilitazione in psichiatria, Modena [Mosher was one of the speakers], 1990 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Psychiatric medication, drug trials - clippings (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Report of State Pharmacy and Therapeutics Committee Discussion of Departmental Treatment Philosophy [Montgomery County?], April 4, 1989 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Schizophrenia: Is There an Answer? [NIMH booklet, photocopy] (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Seminar materials (various topics), 1999-2001 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Semrad, Elvin V.: on psychosis (article by Semrad and notes by Mosher) (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Sharav, V. H. "Children in Clinical Research: A Conflict of Moral Values," InFocus, 2003 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Soteria: progress reports, drafts, notes, 1981 1988-92 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Soteria: Final Progress Report, Mar. 14, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - "Soteria: A Manual,", 1972 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Soteria Manual, with cover letter, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Soteria - news clippings, 1973-80 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Soteria: miscellaneous materials (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - "Still Crazy after all These Years" (San Diego Weekly Reader) and response (1 of 2), January 2003 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - "Still Crazy after all These Years" (San Diego Weekly Reader) and response (2 of 2), January 2003 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Email correspondence re de Wyze article on Mosher [Still Crazy...], 2003 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Photographs
    - Photographs of Mosher (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Photographs of Mosher (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Photographs of Mosher (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Photographs of Mosher,, and, 1973 1979 undated (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Photographs from conference/meeting, undated (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Photographs from meetings, undated (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Photographs from a reunion, with letter, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Lucca slides (black and white images) (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Slides for talk(s) (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Oversize and AV materials
    - Oversize licenses and certificates (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - 2 binders of articles (reprints, photocopies, web-based printouts) on drug treatments and schizophrenia (Box 9, Folder 2-3)
    - The 2nd Annual Dr. Ephraim T. Lisansky Lecture, April 14, 1996, Loren R. Mosher, "The influence of research on health policy: walking the razor's edge; some things are better left unsaid.", 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Soterialand/1972. Dept. mental Health Service. Delivery date: 9/8/98; 14 minutes [2 copies], 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - T.A.M.C. Loren Mosher "Community mental health systems - user friendly?", 17 April 1992; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - "Nightline", 3/28/97; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Abschied von Babylon. Ein film von Nikola Bock, 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - The Drugging of our Children. A Gary Null Production, 2005; 10.1; 1 optical disc(s) (DVD) (Box 10.1U)
    - Seminar--Serious Mental Illness; Dr. Loren Mosher, SDSU School of Social Work guest, 10.2; 1 optical disc(s) (DVD) (Box 10.2U)
    - International Approaches to Assisting the Severely Mentally Ill, Dr. Loren R. Moser; JU87-209, 10.3; 1 optical disc(s) (DVD) (Box 10.3U)
    - Loren Mosher, 2004; 10.4; 1 optical disc(s) (DVD) (Box 10.4U)
    - Connecting Thoughts in Memorium Loren Mosher, 2004; 10.5; 1 optical disc(s) (DVD) (Box 10.5U)
    - Use of medications, undated; 10.6; 1 optical disc(s) (DVD) (Box 10.6U)
    - T's family, 2/24/93; 10.7; 1 optical disc(s) (DVD) (Box 10.7U)
    - Original Best Picture [patient interview?], 10.8; 1 optical disc(s) (DVD) (Box 10.8U)
    - Loren Mosher presentation, 1 computer file(s) (PPT)
    - Bola Mosher; London interview, 1 computer file(s) (PDF) (Box 10)
    - Slide box 1 (text, illustrations, etc. on Big Pharma, Soteria, Milieu, C-PMA, Community Mental Health) (Box 11)
    - Slide box 2: text, illustrations, etc. on cost & context, Myth - Soteria, context & myths (Box 11)
    - 1988 Family therapy Network Symposium "Schizophrenia and the Family" Carol Anderson, Agnes Hatfield, Loren Mosher. Tape 1 and Tape 2; Strategies for Schizophrenia. Psychiatry Vol. 5 No. 19, Oct. 11, 1976. Includes Loren Mosher's "Implications of Soteria's model of madness"; Dr. Loren Mosher interviewed by Craig Fees, 9 November 1993; La Questione Psichiatrica, Trieste, 6-10-88; Mary Barnes by David Edgar; Alma and Joyce, Nov. 6, 1984, Rx ingredients; "Soteria: An alternative to hospitalization," Loren Mosher. The Search for Mental Health 1976; OR 505 Alternatives to hospitalization for children and adolescents. American Orthopsychiatric Assoc. Tape 1 and Tape 2; OR 512 Psychological rehabilitation: an effective intervention for mental health system veterans. American Orthopsychiatric Assoc. Tape 1 and Tape 2; American Psychological Association 103rd Annual convention. August 1995. Consulting for a paradigm change - the overreliance on the medical model [LM was on of the presenters] 2 tapes; Connection - Mad in America 2/18; Boss - 7/15/87; Bleuler - 7/15/87, 17 audiocassette(s) (Box 11)
    - Computer files, 72 computer media (Box 11)
    - 3 wooden plaques: Community Leadership Award from St. Luke's House, Inc. 1996; Appreciation for Services to the Joint Committee on Schizophrenia, New York State Psychiatric Association, 1981; and Appreciation for Outstanding dedication and service to the Mental Health Consumer of Montgomery County, 1991 (Box 12)
- Publications, Series 2; 6 box(es)
  - Journal articles (as numbered by LRM):
    - Publication. #1: "Carcinoma of the Liver and Postnecrotic Cirrhosis: Report of a Case and Review of Carcinomas of the Livers Seen at Stanford from 1919 to 1959," Stanford Medical Bulletin, 18, no. 2 (May 1960). (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - [Publication #2]: "A Clinical Trial of Alpha-Methyldopa in Elated States," by Mosher, Klerman, and Greaney, The American Journal of Psychiatry, 122, no. 10 (April, 1966). (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Publication #3: "Life History Differences in Identical Twins Discordant for Schizophrenia," by Pollin, Stabenau, Mosher, and Tupin, American Journal of Orthopsychiatry, XXXVI, no. 3 (April 1966). (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Publication. #4: "Schizophrenia and Crisis Theory," by Mosher, Menn, and Goveia (presented at Annual Mtg. of the American Orthopsychiatric Association, 1972.). (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Publication #5: "Serum Macroglobulin (S19) in Families of Monozygotic Twins Discordant for Schizophrenia," by Stabenau, Pollin, and Mosher, American Journal. of Psychiatry. 125: 1 (July 1968). (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Publication #6: "Prevalence of Physical Illness in Parents of Identical Twins Discordant for Schizophrenia," by Guggenheim, Pollin, Stabenau, and Mosher, Psychosomatic Medicine, Vol. XXXI, No. 4, July-August 1969). (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Publication #8: "Father Absence and Antisocial Behavior in Negro and White Males," Acta Paedopsychiatric 36,1969. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Publication #9: "Schizophrenogenic Communication and Family Therapy" Family Process, 8, no. 1 (March 1969). (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Publication #10: "Special Report on Schizophrenia," prepared by Mosher and Staff of Clinical Research Branch, Division of Extramural Research Programs, National Institute of Mental Health (March 1969). (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - "Current Studies on Schizophrenia," by Mosher and Feinsilver, International Journal of Psychoanalytic Psychotherapy, 2, no. 1, (1973). (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Publication #11: "Study of Monozygotic Twins Discordant for Schizophrenia," by Stabenau, Pollin, Mosher, Frohman, Friedhoff, and Turner, Arch Gen Psychiat, 20 (Feb. 1969). (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Publication #12: "Nicotinic Acid Side Effects and Toxicity: A Review," Amer. J. Psychiat. 126: 9, (March 1970). (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - #13 "The Several Worlds of Schizophrenia: Is a synthesis possible?," Human Context: 2(3), 450- 476 (1970). (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Publication #14 [not found] (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Publication #15: "Methodological issues in research with groups at high risk for the development of schizophrenia," by Mosher and Wynne (no date). (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Publication #16:"Madness and the Community" Attitude, Vol. 1, No. 7 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Publication #17: "New Treatment Systems for Schizophrenia," Schizophrenia 3, no. 2 (Second Quarter 1971). (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Publication #19: "Special Report: Schizophrenia," prepared by Mosher and Feinsilver, 1970-71(?); U.S. Dept. of Health, Education, and Welfare, Public Health Service, Health Services and Mental Health Administration, National Institute of Mental Health. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - #20 (article: "Family Art Evaluation: Use in Families with Schizophrenic Twins" by Mosher and Kwiatkowska, The Journal of Nervous and Mental Disease, Vol. 153, No. 3, 1971) (Box 1, Folder 19)